<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An eye-salve for the city of London: discovering unto them the great engagement that lyes upon them in point of duty and interest, to joyne speedily with the kingdome for the restoring of His Majesty, and the re-setling of the lawfull government and peace of this nation. / By a lover of peace and truth.</title>
            <author>Lover of peace and truth.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84319</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E445_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201958</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862432</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862432</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161740</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84319)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161740)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E445[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An eye-salve for the city of London: discovering unto them the great engagement that lyes upon them in point of duty and interest, to joyne speedily with the kingdome for the restoring of His Majesty, and the re-setling of the lawfull government and peace of this nation. / By a lover of peace and truth.</title>
                  <author>Lover of peace and truth.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royalists --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161740:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EYE-SALVE FOR THE CITY OF <hi>LONDON:</hi> Diſcovering unto them the great Engagement that lyes upon them in point of Duty and Intereſt, to joyne ſpeedily with the Kingdome for the reſtoring of His Majeſty, and the re-ſetling of the lawfull Government and Peace of this Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Lover of Peace and Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 24.21.</hi>
               </bibl> My ſonne, feare thou the Lord and the King, and meddle not with them that are given to change.</q>
            <p>Printed in the yeare, 1648.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:161740:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:161740:2"/>
            <head>A ſhort Advertiſement to the Common-Councel of the City, and to all other Citizens, concerning the Contents of this Book.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen and Fellow-ſubjects,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a wiſe ſaying of a wiſe man, <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.6. <hi>Faithfull are the wounds of a friend, but the kiſſes of an enemy are deceitfull.</hi> And truely I am afraid you have had many ſuch kiſſes, and ſome of them, too like that of <hi>Judas,</hi> from the mouthes of pretended Diſciples, and Apoſtles as it were, who have ſoothed you up in your ſins, and ſought by faire words and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull colours, to dawbe over your flawes with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter: not to cure them, but to cover them, and to make ſure your ruine. I am ſorry to think that this hath been the buſineſſe of ſome Pulpits now ſo lately amongſt you, when the paint of Religion and Piety that hath been drawn over the horrid miſchiefe you wot on, is growne ſo fading and withered, and the ugly wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſtrumpet of Sedition is ſo viſible to the whole Kingdome, and ſhe forſaken and hated of ſo many that formerly doted upon her ſophiſticate beauty, that yet they ſhould be ſo impudent, and goe about to make ſo cleere a merchandize of your ſoules unto your faces, as to
<pb facs="tcp:161740:3"/>perſwade you ſtil to entertain ſuch a loathſome and hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full —in your boſomes. I ſhall ſay no more to them at this time, but as <hi>Michael</hi> did once unto Sathan, <hi>The Lord rebuke them;</hi> Not unto you concerning them, but to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe you, that you will not ſo far betray your ſelves to thoſe that <hi>walk in the way of Cain, and run greedily after the error of Balaam for reward,</hi> having received, as you may too probably ſuſpect, the hire of your deſtruction, as to let them bewitch you into an incurable condition.</p>
            <p>As for me, I come to you with ſincere affections, both to your owne and the Kingdomes good. And though you may perceive me to deale plainly with you, yet I aſſure you I meane nothing but benefit unto you. If my pen have the ſharpneſſe of a launce in ſome things, yet you will find my Inke to have Balſome in it in other things. My ſearching is to make way for healing. Let me entreat you not to be impatient of the one, and I hope you will find much comfort in the other. <hi>Genus quoddam Martyrii eſt non ignobile,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine, reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentem aequanimiter ferre.</hi> It is a noble kind of Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to endure the ſtroak of Reproof with a patient mind.</p>
            <p>Be pleaſed therefore to reade it through without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, and I doubt not but you may find Cordials at laſt for every irkeſome purgative in the beginning. <hi>Let me not become your enemy becauſe I tell you the truth.</hi> I will ſay no more for my Apologie then what <hi>Quintius the Conſul</hi> ſaid once unto the <hi>Romanes</hi> in a caſe not in all things unlike unto this wherein I have to doe with you. The Romanes it ſeemes were then in a ſlothfull and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid condition, and he doth not ſpare like an honeſt man to tell them of it, that he may rouze them from it. <hi>Sedemus deſides domi,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>mulierum ritu inter nos
<pb facs="tcp:161740:3"/>altercantes, praeſenti pace laeti, nec cernentes ex otio illo brevi multiplex Bellum rediturum. We ſit lazily at home, like women holding debate with one another. We pleaſe our ſelves with our preſent peace, not fore-ſeeing how many wars will ſhortly riſe up out of that ſloth.</hi> And as he draws to a concluſion with them, ſo give me leave to make my entrance with you: <hi>His ego gratiora dictu alia eſſe ſcio: ſed me vera pro gratis loqui, etſi meum ingenium non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veret, neceſsitas tamen cogit; vellem equidem vobis placere Quirites, ſed multo malo vos ſalvos eſſe: qualicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>, erga me animo futuri eſtis.</hi> I ſhall Engliſh it thus: <hi>I know well that other language might be more acceptable unto you then that which I am now to deliver: But although mine owne diſpoſition did not admoniſh me, yet very neceſsity doth exact it of me, rather to ſpeak things true then accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. I would moſt gladly pleaſe you</hi> (Grave Senatours, and Citizens) <hi>But I much more deſire your ſafety and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, however you ſhall be affected toward me.</hi> And ſince there are ſo many that are plotting both within you and about you, to engage you to expoſe your ſelves unto ruine, that you may ſerve the turnes of their ſinnes and wicked intereſts. Be not offended at one plaine-dealing friend, that deſires to move you unto your owne preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161740:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161740:4"/>
            <head>To the City of <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Re you not aſhamed to ſee the ſpirit of Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Loyalty, moving ſo cheerfully in the Country round about you, for the reſtoring of His Sacred Majeſty, and the re-ſettlement of the Peace and Government of this Kingdom, and you to ſit ſtill and ſay nothing, nor put to the leaſt of your fingers to ſet it forward? Were you ſo early and ſo haſty to be a wretched example unto others, in kindling the flames of Sedition and Confuſion in this Nation, to ſatisfie the luſt of your pride and rebellious hearts; and wil no exactions of Conſcience ſtir you up? nor no examples pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke you, to bring ſo much as a bucket to the quenching of them? Have you no regard of the miſeries and oppreſſions of your pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and gracious King, trampled upon by baſe and unworthy vaſſals, with more then Turkiſh and Heatheniſh cruelty? Suffering ſo many barbarous injuries and perſecutions in his Crowne, in his Honour, in his Liberty, in his Revenue, in his Queen, in his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, in his Servants, in his very ſoul, being not ſo much as allowed a Chaplain to aſſiſt him in Religion, no regard of the ſad and blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding condition of this Church and Nation, ready to be embroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againe in blood and ruine, and to become a prey unto forraign Nations? no ſenſe of the heavy Calamities that hang over your City, which is like to be made the prize of our enſuing contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Do you not yet ſee that there is no way probable upon earth, no courſe allowable or approveable from heaven, to repaire thoſe ruines which are already broken in upon us, or to diſperſe thoſe other clouds that threaten us round about, but our returning unto God, and reſtoring of his Anointed? Are the eyes of the whole Kingdome opened, and are you onely incurably blind? Are the Country people ſenſible of their engagements, and can your City
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161740:5"/>be ſo ſtupid as to think themſelves leſſe obliged than the reſt? Have not your ſins as well as theirs, been the ſad Factors of our Nationall miſeries? Were there no fountains in this City that fed the flood of theſe publike calamities, that have ſo overwhelmed the King and people? Was it not a ſeditious and ſeduced party in this City, that by their tumults and miſ-guided zeale firſt violated the liberty and freedome of the Parliament, by threatning, and over-awing the loyall and faithfull members thereof? Was it not the undutifull carriage of ſome unruly people there unto His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, ſiding againſt Him with the forgers of Confuſion, that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Him to withdraw Himſelfe for the ſafety and preſervation of His Perſon, to avoid the fury of their popular tempeſts?</p>
            <p>Was there nothing of the wombe and of the nurcery here of this accurſed and monſtrous rebellion? had it no ſupply from the ſtrength and riches of this City? Was it not the Mony, and the Plate, and the Thimbles, and the Bodkins, and the Magazines, and the Armes, and the Contributions, and the Forces of this City as well as others, that hath continually ſupported and kept in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that ungodly deſigne that hath brought ſuch deſolation upon theſe three Kingdomes? were there no treaſuries emptyed here, to purchaſe the bloud and ruine of this Nation, and turne this Paradice into an <hi>Aceldama?</hi> Have there none of your plumes been carryed to the feathering that neaſt, where the <hi>Cockatrices</hi> have layed and hatched up their poyſonous Iſſues that have been ſo venemous and deadly in the deſtruction of our People? Have none of thoſe Seeds of Schiſme and <hi>Faction,</hi> of <hi>Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemies</hi> ſprung up out of your field, that have ſince ſo over-ſpread the face of this waſted Church of <hi>England?</hi> Can you ſay, you are more free then all others, from thoſe oppreſſions and perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and injuſtices and deſtructions, that have ſeized upon the King and People, to the waſting of ſo many Families, the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>undoing of ſo many thouſands of poore people? And is all this nothing to be Anſwered for? Is there no reſtitution due from you, for ſo many injuries you have cauſed? were you with the firſt in the miſcheif? and can you hope that it will content either God or Man, that you ſhould be the laſt in the remedy? Were you ſo active, ſo buſie, ſo zealous, ſo bountifull in the work of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and can you not ſo much as ſtirre a foot for peace, for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161740:5"/>reſtoring of your wronged and abuſed KING, and for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of your waſted and diſtreſſed Country: miſtake me not. I lay not this charge upon your whole City, I doubt not but there have been all this while, and are ſtill many loyall hearts that have groaned and ſighed to ſee the growth of theſe miſchiefs. Neither yet would I be ſo underſtood, as if I intended to imbitter the hearts of any, againſt all thoſe that have been heretofore engaged in unlawfull actions; we ſhall eaſily admit the fault to have been more in your Leaders, and Falſe-teachers, than in you: we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve you have been ſeduced and abuſed, and that your intentions were not halfe ſo bad as the actions have proved: we preſume many of you were cheated with pretences and colours of making the King Glorious, and reforming the Church and State. Though no ſuch aymes had they been never ſo ſincere in thoſe that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon you, could have juſtified the actions which they were made uſe of to countenance, which being in themſelves e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, can be made good by no circumſtances. But now that you ſee the plaine meaning of this wicked and accurſed Rebellion, and that God himſelf hath begun to ſhew himſelf againſt it: Be not I beſeech you ſtill bewitched to ſide with it. Are you ſo faſt entangled in the ſnare of Sathan, that you cannot ſo much as ſtir to get out of it? conſider the gracious dealings of God with you, how he hath provoked you to emulation by the loyalty of others. The good people of <hi>Surrey</hi> (your neare neighbours) are ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their Oaths of Supremacy and Allegiance, and that no power on earth can abſolve them from them: have you not taken them as well as they? Did not your—Mayor take them at his Inſtallation? Have not all the Officers of your City taken them at their entrance upon their Offices? are they not the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of your Authority and of your honour, of your Charter and Freedome, if you have any of theſe left? Are theſe dreadfull bonds become meer formalities and ceremonies with you? or what Pope have you to abſolve you of them? But perhaps you have ill memories ſince you have drunke of that <hi>Lethe</hi> of your Covenant; it ſeems you have forgotten thoſe ſacred Oaths. But give me leave to remember you a little, and to ſet the great obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of them before your eyes, that you may examine your acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and know your duties by them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:161740:6"/>The Oath of Supremacy is this:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> A. B. <hi>Doe utterly teſtifie and declare in my Conſcience that the</hi> KING'S <hi>Highneſſe is the only ſupreme Governour in this Realm, and of all other His Majeſties Dominions and Countries, as well in all ſpirituall and Eccleſiaſticall things or cauſes, as Temporall:</hi> and if he be the only ſupreme Governour, there is none upon earth either above Him to correct or limit him, to regulate, or interrupt His Power and Authority, or equall to Him to encounter it or juſtle with Him in it, or that can require any duty of ſubjection from you but only in order to and ſubordination under His power, and with reſervation and maintenance of, and without any prejudice to that obedience and ſubjection that we owe unto Him immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately under God, who onely is <hi>higher than the higheſt,</hi> and above the ſupreme upon earth, whoever they be whether Houſes or Armies, you are ſworne to acknowledge His ſuperiority above them. It followeth, <hi>and that no forraine Prince, Perſon or Prelate, State or Potentate, hath, or ought to have any juriſdiction, power, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, preheminence, or authority, Eccleſiaſticall or Spirituall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Realme: and therefore I doe utterly renounce and forſake all forraine Juriſdictions, powers, ſuperiorities, and authorities, granted or belonging to the</hi> KING'S <hi>Highneſſe, His Heires and lawfull Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt clauſe of this Oath is in generall termes, and doth clearly exclude all ſuperiority or equality of power either in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments or people, either domeſtique or forraine, to the power and authority of the King, and that in all cauſes both Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Civill. This part doth particularly exclude the power of the Pope, or forraine Princes, in Eccleſiaſticall and Spirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. If any ſhall aske why inteſtine, as well as forraine power is not mentioned in this clauſe? I anſwer, firſt, it is abundantly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for in the former part of the Oath, and <hi>Tautologyes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not an Oath, which ought to conſiſt as of clearneſſe, for the judgments, ſo of brevity, for the memories of thoſe that take it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the reaſon hereof might be ſomething like that which was auntiently given for the omiſſion of the expreſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion againſt Paricides: that it was an offence ſo great that it was ſuppoſed that none would be ſo wicked to commit it, ſo it may ſeem to be the candour and charity of this law not to ſeem
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161740:6"/>to admit of any ſuch thing as poſſible in this Common-wealth. That any domeſtique members of this body ſhould forget ſo clear and ſo evident a duty, or fall into ſo high and ſo heynous a ſin as to violate the power and authority of their own King.</p>
            <p>But yet if any thing be wanting here, it is ſupplied in the laſt clauſe, which is generall alſo, and runs thus, <hi>and I doe promiſe that from hence forth I ſhall bear faith and true allegiance to the</hi> KING'S <hi>Highneſſe, His Heires and lawfull Succeſſours, and to my power ſhall aſſiſt and defend all juriſdictions, priviledges, preeminences and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities, granted or belonging to the</hi> KING'S <hi>Highneſſe, His Heires and Succeſſours, or united and annexed to the imperiall Crowne of this Realme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where note, firſt, that you have bound your ſelves <hi>to keep faith &amp; true allegiance to His Majeſty, His Heirs and lawful Succeſſours,</hi> that is, That you will faithfully performe your duties of allegiance, obedience and ſubjection unto Him, and them after Him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that you will <hi>to your power,</hi> that is, as much as you ſhall be able by ſtrength, counſell, perſonall ſervice, intelligence, ſupply by your eſtates, or otherwiſe, <hi>Defend</hi> (firſt) <hi>all the Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions belonging to the King and His Crowne;</hi> ſuch is the <hi>Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſupreme Government in this and all other His Kingdoms and Dominions,</hi> with all the <hi>Branches</hi> thereof. The generality and fulneſſe whereof is ſet downe in the Statute of the 24 of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>ch.</hi> 12. where <hi>this Realme of England</hi> is declared to be <hi>an Empire governed by one ſupreme head and King, and the Body politick, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact of all ſorts and degrees of people, ſaid to be bounden, and to owe and beare, next to God, a naturall and humble obedience:</hi> and ſure the Houſes of Parliament in the moſt perfect and uncorrupted conſtitution thereof are yet no Gods, and therefore can challenge nothing of the ſubject before, or in prejudice of, or in competi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with the King; and <hi>the King</hi> is there ſaid <hi>to be inſtitute and furniſhed by the goodneſſe and ſufferance of Almighty God, with ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary, whole, and entire power, preheminence,</hi> authority, <hi>prerogative, and juriſdiction to render and yeild juſtice, and finall determination to all manner of folke reſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s, or ſubjects within this Realme, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſeverall branches of this Juriſdiction of His, you may ſee declared in the ſeverall Laws of this Kingdome,<note place="margin">See Parliament Writs. 1 K. Iam, c. 1.</note> as the <hi>power to Call, prorogue, and diſſolve Parliaments; of making Lawes by His
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161740:7"/>royall and free Aſſent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">25 H. 8.19.</note> 
               <hi>and his Negative voice;</hi> of <hi>Calling Convoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or Aſſemblies of the Clergy;</hi> of <hi>Pardoning Treaſons, Murders, Manſlaughters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">27 H. 8.24.</note> 
               <hi>Felonies,</hi> &amp;c. of <hi>making Juſtices in Eyre, Justices of Aſſize,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtices of Peace, and Juſtices of Gaole-delivery, by Letters Pattents under the Kings Great Seale, in his Name and by autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the King's Highneſſe, and His Heires Kings of this Realme, in all places of His Dominions, at their pleaſure and wills. The power of raiſing Armies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">7 Edw. 1.11 H. 7.18 &amp; 19 H. 7.1. f. 42. Stat. at large. 4 &amp; 5 P. &amp; M. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>and making War, and concluding Peace; granting Commiſſions to Commanders and Officers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The power of all Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Caſtles, Forts,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>within His Dominions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, You have ſworne, <hi>that you will defend all His Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, preheminences and authorities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is ſure <hi>the Liberty of His Perſon, that He ought not to be made a Priſoner by His Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is His priviledge, <hi>to come when He pleaſeth and to ſit in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such is <hi>His exemption from all Judiciall proceeding againſt His Perſon or Authority.</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Iudge <hi>Ienk.</hi> p. 11.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The power <hi>to diſpoſe of His owne Eſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To <hi>chooſe His owne Counſellours and Servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Conferring of the great Offices of the Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>making and diſpoſing of the Great Seale,</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Iudge <hi>Ienk.</hi> pag. 45. &amp; 25 Ed. 3.</note> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all theſe you have promiſed to aſſiſt and defend to your power, binding your ſelves with that dreadfull and ſacred bond,</hi> So help you God, <hi>and the Contents of the Goſpell; ſo that your wilfull failing herein is a renouncing of Gods help by the Goſpell, and ſo of the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now <hi>Conſider this all ye that forget God, lest he pluck you away, and there be none to deliver you.</hi> Aſſure your ſelves this Oath of yours is <hi>upon Record in the Court of heaven,</hi> and will one day be produced, and you called to a reckoning for it. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how you have behaved your ſelves in order to this ſacred Oath, and the Contents thereof, for theſe ſeven years laſt paſt, and repent, oh repent, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider what this Oath requireth of you now. Doe you not clearly ſee, that all the <hi>Juriſdictions and Priviledges,</hi> and <hi>Prehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencies and Authorities of His Majeſty are invaded, and ſpoiled by the inſolencie of wicked and ungodly Rebels?</hi> You have <hi>ſworne</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:161740:7"/>and <hi>engaged your ſoules</hi> to <hi>defend and aſſiſt them to your power,</hi> and you have pawned your ſalvation for it; how doe you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme this when you ſee His Crowne raviſhed from his head? His Sword wreſted out of His hand? Himſelfe robbed not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all His Kingly Power, but of the liberty and comfort that belongs unto the meaneſt Subject? of the liberty of His Perſon? and the liberty of His Conſcience? and you ſit ſtill, and will not ſo much as ſtirre in His defence and aſsiſtance? Oh how will this be anſwered at the day of Judgement? Doe not ſay you have not power to doe it; if you would make uſe of that power that you have, by Gods bleſſing and the aſſiſtance of the whole Kingdome, (which is even ready to joyne with you, and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whereof have begun before you to your ſhame) you may quickly make an end of the buſineſſe, and prevent the ſhedding of much blood, and the ruine and deſtruction of your ſelves and this whole Nation.</p>
            <p>By thus doing, you may ſatisfie the duty of your <hi>Oathes</hi> and of your <hi>Conſciences,</hi> and make ſome <hi>recompence</hi> unto <hi>your Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne</hi> and <hi>your Country,</hi> for thoſe great injuries and miſchiefs that they have ſuffered by the meanes of your City-diſturbers. They expect this reſtitution from you, without which, how can you ever look that your ſins ſhould be forgiven you?</p>
            <p>Doe not bring an incurable <hi>odium</hi> from your King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try upon your ſelves; it may have heavy conſequences hereafter: At leaſt doe not heape Gods wrath upon your ſelves, by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in perjurious leagues with bare-fac'd impieties. Reade the 17. Chapter of <hi>Ezekiel, ver.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16. and ſee what a ſevere revenger God is of perjury, of perjury unto Kings; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſeriouſly upon that queſtion of God, it is a threatning que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, v. 11. <hi>Shall he eſcape</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>that doth ſuch things? or ſhall he breake the Covenant and be delivered?</hi> he meanes not your Nationall Covenant, but the Covenant of fidelity made unto a King; it amounts to thus much, and will come home to you, if you take not heed. They ſhall not eſcape that doe ſuch things, if they repent not, if they continue in them. Read your <hi>Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance,</hi> I cannot ſtand now to ſet the whole before you here, much leſſe to enlarge upon it; only let me mind you of that one clauſe in it, <hi>I will bear true faith and allegiance to His Majesty,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161740:8"/>His Heirs and Succeſſours, and Him and them will defend to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of my power, againſt all conſpiracies and attempts whatſoever, which ſhall be made againſt His or</hi> THEIR PERSONS, (note that) <hi>their Crown and Dignity, &amp;c.</hi> Oh, this hath been bravely kept by ſome, let no mans falſe gloſſes deceive you, <hi>equivocations and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſecret reſervations are all excluded by the very expreſſe words of the Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In truth I am loath to remember you of the Covenant, I wiſh it may be forgotten to all purpoſes, but repentance, leſt it prove a perpetuall Seminary of blood and ruine to theſe Nations. I am ſure it cannot aboliſh the force of your oathes formerly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, nor make void any duty that was due from you to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. But where it joynes with your former oathes and duties, it may aggravate both your ſin and puniſhment, if you performe them not. And did you not there Covenant to <hi>maintain the Kings Perſon and Honour?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am not ignorant of that wicked loope-hole that was left you there to take aime at his deſtruction, through that deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mound that was pretended to be made for His preſervation. But let me tell you, that deceitfull Colluſions in the framing or taking of Oathes, will prove no abatements to our duties, nor to our condemnation in the neglect of them. Thoſe are your ſins, and will not be your excuſes.</p>
            <p>If there be any amongſt you that have not taken any of theſe either Oathes or Covenant, yet the generall duty that they owe to God and his Ordinance, is ſufficient engagement to binde us to the King, as to obey him, and ſubmit unto him, not to reſiſt him, and that <hi>under paine of judgement or damnation,</hi> ſo to <hi>preſerve</hi> Him, to <hi>defend</hi> Him, to <hi>relieve</hi> Him and <hi>ſuccour</hi> Him, to <hi>vindicate</hi> Him from the vile oppreſſion of Traitors and Rebels: And if you doe it not, here I charge you with all the farther miſchiefes that may befall His Sacred Perſon, and with all the blood and ruine, and deſtruction and deſolation that ſhall ſucceed in this Church and State, and ſhall break in upon us for want of your concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence: and remember that you have been admoniſhed. Reade the 26. Chapter of the firſt Booke of <hi>Samuel,</hi> at the 16. verſe and ſee what comfortable newes <hi>David</hi> there tells <hi>Abner</hi> and the <hi>peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> for neglecting the defence of the <hi>Anoynted of the Lord,</hi> though
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161740:8"/>a wicked and ungodly tyrant: and ſee what our Saviour ſaith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Pilate, Joh.</hi> 18.36. and conſider how you will anſwer unto God for your diſorderly carriages to your pious and gracious So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne. It was a queſtion that the hard-hearted Iewes could not anſwer, that <hi>Pilate</hi> asked them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Shall I crucifie your King?</hi> They were not grown ſo impudent in wickedneſſe, as openly to admit of ſo great an impiety, and therefore they evade it, by denying him to be their King, crying out, <hi>We have no King but Caeſar:</hi> and when in the title of his Croſſe they ſaw written, JESUS OF NAZARETH KING OF THE JEWS. They ſeem to look upon it as their ſhame and diſhonour, as a charge of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and horrid treaſon upon them, that he ſhould ſuffer ſo much diſgrace and miſery though but <hi>under the name and title of their King,</hi> and therefore the <hi>chief Prieſts</hi> of the <hi>Jewes</hi> make it their requeſt unto <hi>Pilate</hi> that their honour might not be crucified thereby upon the Croſſe of Chriſt: <hi>Write not</hi> (ſay they) <hi>the King of the Jewes, but that he ſaid I am King of the Jewes.</hi> But the City of <hi>London</hi> can be content to ſee their King trampled on and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and impriſoned, and abuſed, and trodden under foot by thoſe whom they have hired, and to give countenance and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, and protection to thoſe that doe it.</p>
            <p>But doe we not heare ſome (I hope not many of you) ready to cry out now, in oppoſition to all this, <hi>if we forſake the Devill, the Devill will forſake us,</hi> and then what ſhall we doe? we have gone ſo farre in wickedneſſe againſt God, and committed ſuch intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable inſolencies againſt our King, and given ſuch provocations to the loyal &amp; honeſt Party, that we can ſcarce hope for the mercy of the firſt, or pardon of the ſecond, or of reconciliation to the third. This was, indeed it may ſeem, in part the caſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.11. They are noted to have been the higheſt Actors in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion with <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and therefore they were ſlow in entertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the thoughts of bringing the King back, when all the people of the land beſides were earneſt in the buſineſſe: and is not this the very caſe upon the matter of <hi>London</hi> at this time? <hi>of ſuch a clammy and engaging nature is this kind of rebellous wickedneſſe, that when men are gotten into this net of the Devill, it is too hard a matter to get out againe.</hi> The old trick of Sathan, firſt <hi>to engage men in wickedneſſe by preſumption,</hi> and <hi>then to hold them in it by diſpaire.</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:161740:9"/>Such difference is there between the logick &amp; argumentations of the fleſh and ſpirit; the fleſh teacheth men to conclude from wickedneſſe to wickedneſſe. I have committed ſo much ſin, that there is no hope of mercy; that it is to no purpoſe to returne. We have done ſo many and ſo great injuries to our Soveraigne, that there is no way for us but to commit greater, becauſe there is no likelyhood that He ſhould pardon us. But grace and the ſpirit argues thus, We have been the firſt and moſt active in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and wickedneſſe, in chaſing away the King, and in cauſing the ruine of Him and of the Kingdome, therefore we will be firſt and moſt active in repentance, the firſt and moſt active in making amends for our miſcarriages. This former is obſerved to have been the caſe of <hi>Judah</hi> there: <hi>Viros Judae</hi> (ſaith one) <hi>Domi contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat conſcientia ſceleris &amp; perfidiae, quâ prae reliquis tribubus peceâ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, &amp; fortè primi rebellionis Abſalomi fautores ac ſequaces fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t qui perdito Juveni propius frequentiuſque aſſeverant,</hi> the men of Judah were kept at home by the conſcience of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe and perfidiouſneſſe, wherein they had offended more than the reſt of the Tribes, as having been perhaps the prime fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers and followers of the rebellion of <hi>Abſalom,</hi> and having had more neer and frequent commerce and intimacy with that deſperate young man; Look, looke into this glaſſe of <hi>Judah,</hi> and ſee thine owne face <hi>London;</hi> examine your conſciences and deale ſincerely with your ſelves, are not the ſecrets of ſome of your hearts here laid open unto you? He that deales plainly with you loves you beſt. Oh, the wonderfull ſearching power of the word of God! how it laies open the treacheries of mens hearts, that falling downe on their faces they may worſhip God? Is not this your very caſe? the men of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that were not ſo deeply engaged in the rebellion, they are forward and ready <hi>to bring backe their King,</hi> their eyes are opened by the ſtrange judgment upon <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom.</hi> They begin to acknowledge now that they were <hi>ſeduced</hi> and <hi>abuſed</hi> by his <hi>gloſing promiſes,</hi> and <hi>falſe entertaiments.</hi> They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member now the goodneſſe of <hi>David,</hi> and the manifold benefits that they received by his Government, and they were at ſtrife throughout all the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſaying, <hi>the King ſaved us out of the hand of our enemies, and he delivered us out of the hand of the Philistims,</hi> and <hi>now he is fled out of the land for Abſalom,</hi> and <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161740:9"/>whom we anointed over us</hi> (not God, but we) <hi>is dead in Battle; now therefore, why ſpeake you not a word of bringing the King back?</hi> and is not this now in the hearts of all the people of the Land upon the matter at this time? but <hi>Judah</hi> ſits ſtill, being bound like ſome of you in the fetters of their evill conſcience and high impieties. But what does the <hi>good King?</hi> his heart yerneth after <hi>Judah,</hi> all their wickedneſſe could not extinguiſh his love unto them, and herein he was a man after Gods owne heart. He <hi>ſends to Zadok and to Abiathar the Prieſts,</hi> ſaying, <hi>ſpeake unto the Elders of Judah,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Why are ye the laſt to bring the King to his houſe? ſeeing the ſpeech of all Iſrael is come to the King, even to his houſe. Ye are my Brethren, ye are my bones and my fleſh; wherefore then are ye the laſt to bring the King back?</hi> He takes this unkindly &amp; no doubt <hi>the King will take it unkindly:</hi> But yet <hi>Judah</hi> is perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, for ſo it followeth, <hi>he bowed the hearts of all the men of</hi> Judah, <hi>even as the heart of one man; ſo that they ſent this word unto the King, Return thou and all thy Servants: ſo the King returned and came to</hi> Jordan, <hi>and</hi> Judah <hi>came to</hi> Gilgal, <hi>to go to meet the King, to conduct him to Jordan.</hi> They get the honour of it at laſt from all the men of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> oh, let your hearts be bowed alſo, let this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed example worke upon you, let one that heartily wiſheth your good, that longs for your preſervation prevaile with you. Come, though I have been perhaps a little irkſome in ſearching your wounds, yet I have balſome for you if you will be healed. You have highly offended <hi>God</hi> in <hi>violating that Authority that he hath ſet over you.</hi> Yet deſpaire not, he is ready to forgive, if you be but half ſo ready to ſeek it at his hands. Humble your ſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and you cannot faile of mercy. It is his glory to paſſe by great iniquities.</p>
            <p>You have committed great offences againſt a gracious King, this aggravates your ſins, but withall, it is an encouragement to your converſion, <hi>He is a gracious King:</hi> He that is ſo glorious in patience under obdurate Rebels, cannot but be abundant in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to relenting Offenders; and if he had the liberty as <hi>David</hi> had, doubt not, but he would ſend to you as <hi>David</hi> did unto <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah.</hi> Imagine you heard him expreſſing himſelf unto you out of the bowels of thoſe tender compaſſions that are in him. Ye are my Subjects; ye are my children, ye are my bone and my fleſh, ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161740:10"/>deare and precious are ye unto me. I long for your good, I am ready to pardon all. I pity your errours, you have been abuſed as well as I. My armes are open to receive you, let not your armes be engaged againſt me. I am willing to forget all former miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, let God be glorified in all; only perſiſt not now, now you ſee how both I and you have been wronged. I never meant you ill, your <hi>jealouſies</hi> were your oppreſſours, not I; why then are ye the laſt to bring back the King?</p>
            <p>Feare not but that you may more oblige him by your returne unto him, if you doe it ſpeedily, and doe it heartily, then ever you diſ-obliged him by your departure from him. You have been the occaſion of many oppreſſions, and of great ruines to the Loyall people, and to your Country; but you may now (if you pleaſe) make amends for all, and our Chriſtianity engageth us to accept it from you.</p>
            <p>Be not jealous of your friends, let not vaine feares affright you from your ſhare in ſo glorious a work, as is the reſtoring of your King and Country, the re-eſtabliſhing of Religion, and Peace in this Church and Nation.</p>
            <p>Do that which God requires, and leave conſequences to him; <hi>Nouriſh thoſe Serpents no longer in your boſomes, that have returned ſo many Stings for the warmth you have afforded them:</hi> when they are in need of your help, then they fawn upon you; but when they can but think themſelves able to ſubſiſt without you, or to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain themſelves againſt you, then they ſcorn you, and oppreſſe you, and affront you, and deſtroy you; <hi>take heed of thoſe friends that are held unto you onely by the chaines of their owne neceſſities; when they are made ſtrong enough by you, to break thoſe chaines, they are like enough to find other chaines to hamper you withall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider well what it is that makes them flie unto you now; is it not to hide themſelves under your gownes, from the preſent ſtorme that they know not how otherwiſe to avoid? <hi>let them not buy their ſafety, by engaging you unto ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember how you have been paid for your former ſervices; whilſt they had their dependence upon you, then you were their <hi>White Boies, their Darlings, their Patrons;</hi> then you had the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> the <hi>Tower,</hi> and <hi>all:</hi> But when they thought themſelves ſtrong enough without you, to deale with you; what then? then
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161740:10"/>
               <hi>that Army which you fed, and nouriſhed, and ſupported, is brought againſt you.</hi> Then <hi>your Works</hi> are <hi>demoliſhed.</hi> Then they <hi>ride in triumph through your City.</hi> Then they <hi>ſcorn your Preſents. Reject your Remonſtrance,</hi> making enquiry after the Authours of it to bring them unto puniſhment. Then they <hi>deprive you of the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia and the Tower. Impriſon your Lord Mayor and Aldermen: Slaughter your Apprentices:</hi> and moſt wickedly <hi>ſolemnize a day of Thanksgiving for their Murders. Take away your Chaines,</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you to the rapine of the Souldier.</p>
            <p>Remember <hi>the inſtability of their Votes;</hi> one while <hi>when they are low, putting power into your hands:</hi> and then <hi>upon a ſmall ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of ſucceſs, ready to retract it again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Remember the <hi>Affidavit you had lately of the pious reſolutions at</hi> Windſor <hi>againſt you,</hi> and <hi>the worthy repair you have had for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider well <hi>the fallacies</hi> and <hi>the reſerves of their late Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and how little truſt they repoſe in you therein:</hi> reſt not your ſelves upon ſuch falſe friends, that change their Adherences as the weather changes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In their Adverſity they are for you, in their Proſperity they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you make them proſperous, then is it not to make them your enemies? and yet they ſay, your Common Councell hath taken them into protection: well, are you reſolved to make them your Maſters? if you are? I doubt you will find them coſtly ones.</p>
            <p>Let me ask you ſeriouſly, will you be content <hi>to maintaine them in a Warre</hi> againſt the whole <hi>Kingdome?</hi> againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> the <hi>Welch,</hi> the <hi>Iriſh:</hi> Take heed, you are like to find it a chargable undertaking: you know what it coſt you, when you had many more to contribute with you; you will find it ſomething more to maintaine it alone, when your <hi>enemies</hi> are <hi>multiplied,</hi> and your <hi>friends</hi> and <hi>aſſiſtants</hi> have <hi>left you,</hi> and are decreaſed. Beware you engage not your ſelves to an utter ruine. It will be much cheaper, and eaſier for you to recover your peace, then to procure your deſtruction; and which doe you think is the better merchandiſe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſtore the King, and you may repaire your Honour, preſerve your Lives, ſecure your Eſtates, re-inforce your Trade, re-eſtabliſh your Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you will play the other game of Rebellion, <hi>remember your
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161740:11"/>ſtakes;</hi> all theſe wil be put in the mouth of danger: and what think you of your <hi>ſouls?</hi> will they be ſafe? And what think you of your <hi>liberty?</hi> have you not <hi>ſworn</hi> to maintain the <hi>Lawes</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of the Kingdome? doe you not ſee what <hi>liberty</hi> grows at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter?</hi> remember the work there upon Tueſday the 16 of <hi>May,</hi> thoſe <hi>veſperae Weſtmonaſterienſes,</hi> thoſe Weſtminſter veſpers, when ſo much cruelty was uſed againſt your Neighbours for but ſo much as <hi>petitioning for Peace.</hi> What <hi>freedome</hi> is left us, if we may not ſo much as <hi>aske</hi> our <hi>freedome?</hi> what ſecurity can we have ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our <hi>lives</hi> or <hi>liberties,</hi> under them, who <hi>take away our lives</hi> for <hi>but asking our liberties?</hi> Is this the <hi>freedome</hi> you have <hi>fought for</hi> and <hi>purchaſed</hi> at ſo deare a rate, with the waſte of your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Conſciences? (I hope all the Kingdome will be ſenſible of this <hi>liberty</hi>) for ſhame awake and joyne with your Country to redeeme your King, and your ſelves from ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Let it not be the diſhonour of our Nation (by your meanes) that the <hi>Scots</hi> were faine to be the Redeemers of our KING. Prevent the coming in of forraine Nations, leſt they fall in love with your treaſures, and make you pay deare for that which you would not have at a cheaper rate.</p>
            <p>I muſt tell you, <hi>whoever doth this work without you, you of all men are like to be their Pay-masters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well, doe not make your ſelves uncapable of pardon: do not heap judgments upon your ſelves. <hi>How long halt you between two Opinions? if Mammon be God, ſerve him: If the Lord be God, ſerve him:</hi> If <hi>Fairfax</hi> be King, ſerve him: If CHARLES be King, reſtore Him.</p>
            <p>You know what right the <hi>King</hi> hath to you; but who made them at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> or <hi>Windſor</hi> to be <hi>Kings</hi> over us? what title can they plead to Governe us? or how come you or we to be their Subjects? have they it by election? who choſe them to be Kings? have they it by ſucceſſion? where is their royall pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree? have they it by conqueſt? it's like they would have it ſo. But (by their leaves) the matter is yet in queſtion, and you and we are the wretchedſt ſlaves alive (for ought I know) if we will admit it, when it is ſo eaſie to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to deale plainly with you as a friend, The truth is, you are look'd upon as the great obſtacles of the happy reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:161740:11"/>of this Nation. As the prolongers of the preſent miſeries thereof, the great queſtion hangeth upon your reſolutions, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Nation ſhall be engaged in another bloudy War or no?</hi> If you will be honeſt and Loyall, you may prevent it by Gods grace, and make a ſpeedy end of our calamities, by reſtoring the KING, and re-eſtabliſhing the Lawes; it wants but your <hi>fiat</hi> under God, and it is even done already. And thereby you ſhall bring honour upon your ſelves, and endeare unto you the hearts of your Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign and this whole Nation, and procure the peace of your owne conſciences by diſcharging ſo great a duty unto God.</p>
            <p>If you will ſtill perſiſt in your cowardiſe and wickedneſſe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this warning and admonition which you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, be ſure you be able to anſwer for all the bloud, and ruine, and deſtruction that followeth; and that you know how to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure your ſelves from that great ſhare of it, that is like to befall you.</p>
            <p>And take heed of the ſaying of the Prophet to <hi>Amaziah,</hi> 2 Chron. 25.16. <hi>I know that God hath purpoſed to deſtroy thee, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſte done this, and haſte not hearkned to my councell.</hi> And remember what meſſage <hi>Mordecay</hi> ſent to <hi>Eſther,</hi> Eſth. 4. v. 13. <hi>Thinke not with thy ſelfe that thou ſhalt eſcape, &amp;c. for if thou alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether holdeſt thy peace at this time, then ſhall there enlargement and deliverance ariſe to the Jewes from another place, but thou and thy Fathers houſe ſhall be deſtroyed, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider of it in time and be wiſe; you will in the end find the French ſaying to be true, <hi>C'eſt la grand fineſſe du monde d'eſtre honeſte,</hi> it is the fineſt trick in the world to be honeſt; this is the beſt <hi>huſbandry</hi> and the beſt <hi>policy.</hi> Go therefore ſpeedily in the firſt place, humble your ſelves to God for what is paſt, aske his pardon, reſolve upon amendment; Let there be a <hi>Common Hall</hi> of your City called, it is juſt it ſhould be ſo, in a matter of ſo great and generall concernment, joyn your ſelves together as one man; ſend to thoſe at <hi>Weſtminster</hi> to require the enlargement, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, the re-enthroning of your KING according to the ſplendour of his Royall Anceſtors, and the re-inforcing of the known Lawes and legitimate Government of this Land, together with the Liberties of the Subject, by Disbanding thoſe Forces
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161740:12"/>that tyrannize over all. If they refuſe peaceably to doe it, you know what you have to doe. <hi>The God of Heaven direct you, and work upon your hearts; to his Glory, and the recovery of this poor Church and Nation.</hi> Farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>A Poſt-ſcript.</head>
            <p>SInce I writ this advice unto you, I have heard that there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Liſted in your City to Engage with the Rebels againſt the Loyall Subjects of <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Surrey,</hi> &amp;c. a word or two therefore to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; if you ſhal go on in any ſuch employment, take this along with you; That as you engage your ſelves againſt your Oaths, your Covenants, your Proteſtations against God, and your King, and your owne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, for the maintenance of Tyrants and Oppreſſours, and for the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Innocent bloud, and for the deſtruction of your owne Liberties; So you muſt expect a reward anſwerable to your worke, to be abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by the people of the Kingdome: and if God for your ſins ſhall ſuffer you to proſper in ſo wicked an enterpriſe, remember that ſuch proſperity is the way to deſtruction and damnation; and if hereafter you ſuffer the greateſt ſhare of that ſlavery which you now ſhall fight for againſt thoſe that ſtand for you and the Kingdomes Rights, you will pay dear for ſo bad a bargain; but it will be a juſt returne upon your baſe and traytorous enterpriſes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
